great so uh what I was hoping Carl um is
that we could get your thoughts on uh
how the whole uh active inference
framework could be applied to something
that uh we've been developing and uh I
don't know if if you had a chance to
look at any of this stuff but I'll just
give you a brief uh you know kind of a
brief summary so that it's clear what
what we've got and then and then I have
some basic questions and then a couple
of wacky ideas to to kind of bounce off
of you and see what see what you think
so the the basic thing is this that what
what what I was trying to do is to have
a very uh basil model of um distributed
uh intelligence and the idea was that uh
we were interested in um unexpected
competencies in places where unlike in
biology you know in biology no matter
how simple your model you never have all
the information about mechanisms and
somebody can always say well there is a
mechanism for that you just haven't
found it yet right so we wanted
something that was incredibly uh simple
incredibly transparent uh deterministic
something that everybody thinks they
know what it does and then we can we can
apply some of the approaches that we
take in my lab about taking something
that doesn't seem cognitive and saying
okay but what what actual competencies
might it have right and so we chose this
thing called sorting algorithms and so
these are the same uh simple algorithms
that all computer science students study
for you know and they've been studied
for decades and then we made a couple of
uh a couple of twists to it is that we
visualize their progress from being a
jumbled set of digits to an ordered set
of digits as a kind of a traversal of of
space right so the idea is they start in
different locations and they all sooner
or later they all end up in in one
location where everything is and so once
once you view it as as as navigating
that space then you can ask some
questions about what are their
competencies in navigating that space
under under odd perturbations one of the
perturbations that we made was the um
introduction of what we call broken
cells or or barriers in the space so if
the algorithm wants to swap two numbers
in order to proceed in its in its
sorting trajectory well one of the
numbers could be broken it doesn't move
you can't you can't move and so and and
we have two kinds of broken numbers ones
that um never initiate swaps and ones
that actually never uh never swap no
matter you know who initiates them and
so that allows us to ask uh questions
about uh things like delayed
gratification in other words can it go
further from it if if it encounters a
barrier can it go further away from its
goal in order to then acquire gains
afterwards and this is you know William
James talked about this of course as H
as an important type of Basil
intelligence and um and that and that
breaks a common assumption with these
algorithms which is typically you assume
that the material is is um robust in
other words when you when the algorithm
says to to do something it gets done but
but in our case not necessarily and we
never introduced this is important we
never introduced any extra code to check
if things got done it's it's the
standard algorithm so it just keeps on
rolling there is no code to see how am I
doing did things work out no no code for
any of that the second thing we did was
to um break the uh the the the general
version of this is centralized so
there's like this omnicient controller
and it's following one of several
algorithms to kind of move numbers
around and we got rid of that and
instead made it all bottom up so every
digit AKA every cell now has its own uh
version of the algorithm running and it
has a a li local view of who its
neighbors are and it's just following
the steps of the algorithm to try to
improve its local environment that there
is no more global global control so it's
distributed and uh and and you know we
learned a few things we learned that a
the distributed version of this works
quite well um it actually you know they
do sord nicely so so that's great we did
see some delayed gratification in the
sense that if you if you sprinkle in
some broken cells it actually will go
backwards and unsort the string a little
bit and then effort to then go around
the the defect as it were so that's kind
of cool but the most kind of surprising
thing which is what um I'd love to get
your your take on is this um we because
now it's distributed and every cell is
following its own algorithm that enables
us to do an experiment that otherwise
you couldn't do which is to make a
chimeric string and it's what we do in
developmental biology when we put
together you know axotal cells and frog
cells and now you get this frog aot and
you can ask questions like well what
shape is it going to have right so so
what you can make is a chimeric string
where some of the numbers are following
one algorithm some of them are following
a different algorithm and again there is
this is important there is no code to uh
determine either your own or your
neighbor's algot type and algot type is
a word that Adam cone for this like um
you know what algorithm what what set of
properties are you actually following a
policies are you actually following so
there is no code for any of that but we
know um which which algot type all the
cells are so that and and and that also
works okay Chic strings also sort sort
them sort the arrays and that's fine
what we then did was we asked basically
a developmental biology question was to
say okay at any particular point during
its Journey what is the distribution of
algot types within the string and what
we know and and we Define of a quantity
called um clustering which basically
just means uh you look you look next to
you and what what's the probability that
the your neighbor next to you is the
same algot type as you are so what
happens is that in the very beginning
that probability is 50% because the
algot types are randomly assigned to the
digits so 50% that's our Baseline at the
very end it's also 50% because at the
end everybody has to be sorted and there
is no relationship between the actual
sort order of the numbers in the algot
type so again it's 50% but the wild
thing is that in between those two
points if you actually plot that curve
over time it actually goes like this and
in between it's quite a bit higher even
if it's statistically very significantly
higher than 50% and what we see is
clustering significant um tendency of
cells with the same algot type to locate
close together eventually the the the
inevitable the inevitable physics of the
algorithm will yank them apart and make
sure that everybody's in numerical order
but until that happens they enjoy some
amount of clustering with their you know
with their cons specific so to speak
until then and so you know any thoughts
you might have but more specifically
like one hypothesis the one could make
even though there's no explicit
mechanism for this but it might be a you
know an emergent thing could they be
preferring to be next to their neighbors
because their neighbors be be ones of
the same algot type are more predictable
right it's it's less surprised you're
less surprised when you're sitting next
to somebody who's following exactly the
same policies as you are so so I'm
curious what you think about that and
I'm curious um if there you know what
what might be uh a set of experiments
that we could do to test that that
what's going on here is some sort of
implicit surprise prize minimization
even though there's no actual code for
it so I'll stop there and and listen to
what you've got to
say sorry um I think you're still
muted I was saying that was a very
succinct and clear and nice summary I I
reread the paper a couple of days ago
just to refresh s um my memory for this
conversation um so I didn't realize that
that was the um that final cam
um demonstration was U sort of you know
the most intriguing from your point of
view um but indeed the way you express
it you that that does call for um um
further analysis understanding and
numerical experiments um so overall
um just to um endorse the choice of the
Sorting algorithm as if you like a
minimal um kind of of uh
self-organization um I think that you
know that the self-organization word
needs to be um center stage in terms of
uh you know what you're trying to
understand here um and framing like that
it does remind me a lot of
self-organizing maps I don't know if you
remember Vander murgs um uh treatment
and people who's this Peter Dian
supervisor I've forgotten now
um so this notion of self-organizing
maps as a very sort of btic aspect of
self-organization I think um certainly
puts sorting like algorithms um um
center stage in terms of biological
self-organization particularly in things
like the visual cortex and why you get
um that kind of um pin wheel
architecture for example where
where receptive field properties tend to
cust together in a smooth way and you
get all sorts of interesting symmetry
breaking when you're trying to represent
say a 5D perceptual space on a 2d
manifold so that does strike me having
this sort linear linear sorting
algorithm um and without really having
not thought about it before but
certainly the the the Dual um the Dual
pressure to find a free energy
minimizing
solution viewing free energy as an
extensive quantity in more simply you
know the collective free energy being
the joint free energy minimum solution
you're asking your where the free energy
dis bounds the likelihood of um this
particular Arrangement um then you're
looking for um the precise functional
form of the free energy um and um if
you've got this kind of um opponency
between the similarity of the algorithm
and the similarity of the content the
value then I can certainly see
interesting behaviors arrive arise in
exactly the same spirit that you get
these interesting um structures in not
epithelia but in in the functional
specialization of of cortical
representations of sensory epithelia um
that try to sort of pack what you three
dimensions into one dimension or are
accountable to two kinds of constraints
so I'm you know again without really
thinking about it because I wasn't I
wasn't anticipating that particular
question but I think what you would be
um the first thing that you would be
looking for is basically what is the
lran or the energy function that is
being minimized so you could regard this
as um the Sorting algorithm as a um or
an application of the Sorting algorithm
as a process um that is trying to
minimize some energy function very much
in the spirit of Mark of random Fields
but in your instance you've just got a
one-dimensional field but this the the
the technology of markof random Fields I
think would be apt to try to understand
the functional forms of the energy
functions um where under the special
constraint which of course is the one
that you're predicating this whole
thesis on the interactions are only
local and therefore any um Collective
Behavior has to be an emergent property
which is truly distributed so the
definitive aspect of a Markoff random
field is you just have local just have
local interactions and that I think
that's a really another important
architectural feature that comes along
with the choice of the Sorting algorithm
which you should foreground um because
you know any distributed Collective um
or emergent Behavior at a scale Beyond
local interactions that emerges is truly
emergent in the sense that your all your
all your interactions are local and of
course that is what the markof field
random field gives you it says that you
can only
express the excuse me the energy
function which is the probability of
getting this particular Arrangement or
these particular numbers um in this
local cque uh you can only express that
in terms of a local energy function and
then of course you could tell sorts of
stories about the importance of that for
machine learning and the like um but you
you you probably want to stick to
self-organization so um yeah and I would
imagine the energy function is now going
to be some simple um um measure of the
um the local differences or the local
gradients uh and of course what you know
what one would anticipate would be a
smoothing um a resolution of as you say
the the other the differences um so I
think that would be one way of
approaching um you know naturalizing
this phenomena in terms of math by just
invoking a um an arbit not a variational
free energy in the spirit of the free
energy principle but just a A lran or
try to identify what is the uh
the generic free energy functional
that's being minimized here um so that
now your view through this um sorting
space or your morphological space um is
now a progression on some wadington
landscape that is defined by the um this
free energy functional um and whether
you can reverse engineer that or not I
you know I don't think it really matters
other than because the I think the nice
aspect of that is then you can talk
about the Dynamics on this free energy
landscape um and one's LED then to very
similar sort of Notions in computational
chemistry and protein folding and the
like you know that there's a very
complex um sorry there is a complex
Wallington landscape or free energy
landscape that self-organization and
computational chemistry um aderes to and
can be understood in terms of freey
Minima indeed most of computational
chemistry sort of follows this um and
indeed that is identifying that
landscape is the whole point of applying
things like large language models or um
deep RL to to sort of protein folding
and um other applications
um so that would that that would be
certainly one view to get a free energy
like um formalism or naturalization of
of this Behavior which I I repeat has
lots of really interesting links with
with um self-organizing Matt's Mark or
random Fields image reconstruction and
self-organization in um you know
certainly in things like the visual
cortex I would imagine any mapped
representation would would would conform
to to uh to to these rules um to get
this into
a to get it into um a free energy
principle uh um story um I think you
would you you'd have to commit to the
notion that each of the cell has its own
boundary and now you're starting to
interpret each number as a thing and in
so doing a acknowledge its openness to
everything else or in this instance just
its neighbors um uh which would require
sort of a bir your formalism of the
bidirectional exchange so that the value
of my nextdoor neighbor is something
that I can sense and you and is uh and
likewise um the broadcasting of my
number to the next door neighbor is
something is an action so you've got
this um
openness that is mediated in the
simplest way which is just the
broadcasting and sensing of one unid
dimensional one number in fact it's a
discrete number um um and viewed like
that that means you can then I think
deploy the free energy principle um in
the sense that any uh non-equilibrium or
um far from
equilibrium steady state which I think
you would probably have here just in
virtue of the fact that there is going
to be some um breaking of detail balance
in the in the itinerant way in which you
move through this space in a
developmental to get to your to your
steady state um and one can imagine well
perhaps not but you know if one puts a
little bit of Dynamics into this that I
would imagine you would evince very very
clearly the breaking of of detailed
balance um and and you know and have you
know those kinds of solenoidal flows um
I mean sorry I I distracted myself just
by um the addition of the Frozen cells
that's one way of breaking um in a sense
uh the detailed balance and you just
Open brackets it's exactly the same
device that um I resol reported to in
the very first paper um um on the uh
Life as We Know It paper when simulating
the little um macro molecules using
Loren attractors that had inherent
Dynamics but to make it interesting you
had to have a small a certain popul
number of the of the synthetic macro
molecules that were insensitive to
influences from other macro molecules
and another proportion that could could
not influence the other one so it's
almost exactly the same Choice uh and
that's what gave it the interesting
Behavior otherwise it just basically
converged either to um a gas or it uh at
a certain temperature it would just
converged to a um to a crystal um so you
both of them being steady state
solutions for energy minimizing
Solutions but things got interesting
when you broke the detailed balance your
symmetry breaking by having this um this
you know this requisite Variety in terms
of um the the frozenness in terms of
action or or sensation so I think that's
another that's another important thing
to foreground that you know this may be
this this kind of requisite variety may
may be absolutely necessary for symmetry
breaking and in this particular instance
breaking detail bounds to get um this
kind of self your know bi biological
Ally plausible or btic kind of self
organization you're unlikely to get that
if um you you you're in the absence of
it in the sense that it would um
converge to a crystal in your instance
just a linear sorting perfect sorting
which which is which is you know just
doesn't have that chimeric or itinerant
I itinerant aspect to it so um sorry
Clos
brackets wait oh yeah
so if you got now an interesting system
that has a non-equilibrium steady state
and in your case actually because you
haven't got Dynamics um it will also be
an equilibrium steady state but it'll
still be a free energy minimizing
solution um then you are perfectly
entitled to interpret the numbers as
things uh and inferring things uh and
all they're trying to infer is the cause
of their Sensations which is just the
value of the numbers on one side and the
other side and they are broadcasting
their inferences through um um um
broadcasting their own number um which
of course will be the average of
um well when sorted it will be the
average of uh the the neighboring
numbers so on that view I think you
could very easily license an active
inference interpretation a thology you
you I mean you wouldn't actually need
this to simulate uh protein folding or
self organizing Maps or anything but you
would be able to say there is a a teic
interpretation of the
self-organization using the rhetoric of
inference and belief updating simply
because we can treat each number now as
a Markoff blanket and the then something
which will never be accessible but we
can um imply or induce um internal to
each number um would um uh could be
interpreted as an inference process and
then the story which you you've already
said what the the answer is that um you
know under the assumption that um I live
in a world that is um maximally
predictable um then everything around me
is the same as me and therefore um um uh
I am going my free energy my variational
free energy um minimizer is now going to
be um
found when there's the least surprising
input and if I believe that everything
is like me um then that will be when the
numbers um that I am sensing in my click
are as similar to my uh the estimate of
the number um um that um the place that
I should be coming back to our sort of
knowing your place paper um and um I
think that that that that that kind of
story um will have to be nuanced for the
same algorithm um so you know I'd have
to think about that a little bit more
but certainly at least at a narrative
level or a conceptual level I think you
can tell the same story there that if
the sequence of moves that I see my
neighbor
doing in relation to what I know about
my
neighbor belies the same underlying
dynamic or algorith your algorithmic um
computations then in some sense they are
predictable if I have exactly the same
algorithm under the hood and therefore
um mathematically speaking um that
should be um that would be the free
energy minimizing solution if I can now
read my broadcasting of the number as a
broadcasting my posterior beliefs about
you know the kind the number that I the
estimate of this local you know
my Niche um um uh in this instance is
just labeled with one you know with one
with one number so that the the number
that I have um is basically um my PRI
belief about my Niche and I'm just now
going to um move my Niche around in a
sort of you know egocentric frame uh
until it is consistent with my Prim
belief that this is my place my Niche is
number 62 for example um and that should
be you should be able to reproduce the
same kind of sorting um either
analytically through showing that um
with an appropriately configured lran or
free energy functional that this the
system operationally is appears to be
minimizing um you can um you can now
write down the generative model and then
show that this can also be interpreted
as an influence process I repeat under
the assumption that um the best way to
make the world predictable is to
surround yourself with things like you
um um which and also of course the
locality assumption that I can only talk
to the person to whom I'm uh immediately
connected so those are some of my
thoughts but a lot of those were
invented on the fly in response to your
question I'm afraid superb um I've got
many questions but Adam why don't you
ask yours yeah so so it strikes me that
up until now we've talked about the
relevant sort of agent as being the
individual number with an algot type you
can think of it as a cell but it strikes
me that there's an interesting macro
phenomenon that that occurs in the
process of
sorting which is that it appears that
the that the list actually
minimizes the kov complexity or the
description length necessary to render
it right so let's just say you've got an
unsorted list with random you know
random distribution of algot types and
there's 10 items in the list you would
need to enumerate 10 numbers and 10
algot types and there's no reason a
priority to think that that would be
compressible in any way I mean maybe
maybe you'd get lucky and there'd be a
string of a certain number a string of a
certain algor type but in the general
case I think you'd actually need to
write out every single entry but as the
list starts to sort itself it actually
starts to create these longer strings of
algot types which means that the minimum
description length actually gets shorter
yeah you still need to write each number
out but you can core screen the
descriptions of the algot types you can
say the first five numbers have the same
you know algot type and then the next
three have the same and so on now that
that's a macro phenomenon but I'm
wondering if there's any any evidence or
any research that suggests that sort of
these self-organizing systems have a
tendency to minimize their description
length to minimize the number of factors
needed or something like that because if
that's the case then it gives us another
view where there's a sort of
emergent complexity minimization
happening at the at the collective level
yes no that's an excellent point
um I think you know the simple answer is
yes absolutely um uh and I can I can
sort of give you my take on the
literature or the citations that you'd
want to appeal to but I I should say
it's going to be a nuanced yes because
of the particular focus on the
clustering of the algo type now the algo
type induces a certain kind of Dynamics
into the game so it's not as simple as a
self-organizing map it's how the map
actually self-organizes so there are a
certain sort of uh there's a process
under you know under under the hood um
and that I think makes it slightly more
complicated than just understanding
self-organized Maps but in terms of um
in terms of um another thing you might
want to look into here of course and you
probably know more about this than I do
but you know this has um a lot of
resonance with artificial life um g
games in the 1990s 1980s it also um
could be um um if you want to so do um
interest inly linked to Steven Wolf's
ruad which is Al Another local um scheme
um that generates everything apparently
uh so there's the same sort of notion so
he has algorithms which he calls rules
and the rules are recursively applied in
a local fashion to generate everything
um including black holes apparently and
and quantum physics and everything uh so
you and just you might
there might be an interesting point of
contact here um with with these uh sorry
but to come back to the simple answer
yes absolutely so um certainly from the
point of view of self-organization as
described by the free energy principle
so notice here um the free energy
principle is just a description of
systems that self-organized to a far
from equilibrium non- equilibrium steady
state it's not a recipe for
sorry in its statement it is not um a a
description of a theological description
of inferential uh processing you are
licensed to to equip your explanation of
this self-organization with reference to
inference but that's an application of
of the free energy principle in itself
it's just a description of any anything
that self-organizes or any things that
self-organize um so in that sense um you
know if there is self-organization under
the could then the free energy principle
has to apply and you can motivate the
free energy principle um along two lines
one would be the sort of playing the
Fineman card which is basically um
derive um looking at the um the
minimization of uh free energy as uh um
an optimization process uh which can be
viewed as a gradient descent on some
Fitness landscape or fre ape or
Wasington landscape um or you can take
the Russian perspective which would be
the col of complexity and from the com
Comm complexity you you you get to uh
solof induction and from that you get to
Universal computation which is the home
of the minimum description length and
minim minimum message length so it's the
algorithmic complexity version of free
energy and so David McCay um wrote a
quirky little paper I think 1992 of of
four where he interpreted variational
free energy in relation to um minimum
message length um using crypto analysis
as a vehicle to tell that story but to
my mind I think wonderfully connected
two different two different perspectives
on exactly the same phenomena the you
know ways of describing self-organizing
systems um that basically both entail a
minimization of complexity um a
simplification an emergence of order of
of a particular sword that entails um um
um either
compression um hence the minimum
description or the minimum message
length uh view from the algorithmic
complexity in terms of um sort of you
know rate coding theorems rate
Distortion theorems and the like um or
you can write it down in terms of
continuous probability distributions and
and sort of follow through from the
finan path integral I think they're both
saying the same thing you know you know
the way I think of this is that the you
know the end point of any
self-organizing thing or set of things
is just going to be the most likely
configuration that they occupy given the
kind of things that they
are um and that basically um means that
you can always describe this um in a
statistical and Theological sense as um
everything um providing an accurate
prediction of what it senses that is
minimally complex in exactly the same
Spirit as um the um the way that you
would frame complexity in terms of um
loss or not loss lossy compression or
minimum description length or minimum um
algorithmic comp complexity so um I
think that if you if you
um if you tell a story that the free
energy is an extensive quantity which
means that all the set of numbers or any
subset of numbers any partition um will
all will all look as if they are
minimizing a free a free energy
functional um then you can I think um
say that you know one view of this
functional is to minimize the complexity
of the arrangement uh which should be
manifested in terms of a minimization of
algorithmic complexity and you can use
is it I never I can never ZL lip or lip
lymph whatever do you know what I'm
talking about was one of these um um
hierarchical sequential entropy measures
um um you know there one way of quickly
enumerating the um the algorithmic
complexity so I think the you if you
could join the dots that would be a
really really powerful um view of this
and indeed you know it would be
interesting if you could
um just using numerical experiments join
the dots um
quantitatively uh in terms of this
handcrafted
inted uh free energy lran just based
upon you given three numbers you have to
now write down an energy function that
is always going to be minimized the
Sorting algorithm so that the end point
um conforms shares the same Minima of
your energy function it could be really
simple it could be this the two
differences squared and added together
something as simple as that um and if
you can prove that the the Minima of
this is the same um uh is is is the same
as the um the end point of your
self-organization then you say this is
one fre energy functional the very much
in the spirit of hot field Nets and
Harmony functions you know in the early
days of um uh neural networks um spin
glass models uh pots models all of these
um Mark of random Fields uh you have to
write down this kind of energy function
and then you just simulate you know you
can you can just do a grad in descent or
rearrangement in order to minimize that
um so that's one very simple kind of
free energy um description of it then
you would have um an inferential one
under an assumed generative model so if
you assume each number actually has a
little mind and a gened model it's
trying to estimate or trying to act upon
its world to realize its beliefs about
what it's sensing you'd have a
variational free energy but then you'd
also have the um the algorithmic um free
energy um um that you could that apply
to any partition and the PO if you can
show that all all three all three sh
share the same minimum at the point of
um attaining non equilibrium steady
state I think that will be really you
know a really nice illustration that all
of these are different facets of exactly
the same thing and you it is a
description of self-organization but
articulated in slightly different ways
but I repeat you once you've got
different
algorithms I I think the process of
sorting
now um um is is somewhat constrained so
that it's
you because you got three different ways
of doing this um they may have different
um they may have different functionals
that are being minimized um and it may
be that but I'm not absolutely sure that
the the order matters and as soon as the
order matters then you've got um
Dynamics in play once you've got
Dynamics in play um that that I think
slightly complicates the simple um um
algorithmic complexity argument because
the the algorithmic complexity um the
universal computation
view um it's not really fit for purpose
to understand Dynamic self-organization
and indeed most people would argue it's
not fit for purpose to to do anything
because it's intractable but it's a
beautiful mathematical object um
does that make
sense yeah um uh so so one thing then
for with Adam's point so so I think
that's a really interesting point and it
raises another question which is if if
if on the compression so on the
compression issue so so if we say that
what you're trying to compress is the
actual list of numbers plus The Ordering
of the algot types then you know
everything as as you guys just said but
I wonder couldn't somebody argue that in
fact there is no list of algot types to
compress there's only the numbers
because it's sort of like you know by
the time you get to the end it's it's
it's kind of like um it's immaterial
information it doesn't do you know it
gets lost by the time you've sorted the
numbers what do you need the list of
algot types for right they're not really
I I don't know I I there's something
here
no I don't think so like if if you take
the position that the algot types aren't
relevant once they stop being used then
you're imposing as an observer an
assumption that the list has finished
moving right but like how do you know
that yeah yeah no that's that's that's
super interesting and and and it's like
the bigger question of there is this
notion of algot types that maybe you
have to take into account what else do
you have to take into account that we
don't know about right like that's
that's one of the things that I see as
as so interesting about this and then
the next thing I was going to ask you
Carl is what's the status of the fact
that like all the things that we were
just talking about about the cells you
know being objects and exchanging
information with their neighbors about
alot types and having predictions I mean
none of that is actually in the
algorithm you can see the algorithm is
like six lines of quote like you can see
what the algorithm is none of that is
there so what's the you know it's more
of a philosophical question you know
what what's the status of of something
and and I had the same question when I
first heard about you know photons and
least action and all that like but
there's no mechanism to know you know to
calculate which path you know is going
to be best for you so do we do with this
what what do we do I'm super interested
in uh these sort of um I don't know
almost almost uh you know uh implicit uh
things that it's doing whereas the
explicit algorithm doesn't have any of
that what what do you think about that
um well probably think the same thing
that you do um I think um
yeah in a sorry in a sense what I was
saying about a nuanced answer once
you're dealing with your isomorphisms
between the local algorithms was exactly
this issue that you're bring to the
table it's not your um yeah it could be
as simple as each algorithm has a
different um objective function
different free energy or lipun of
function um or it could be that they
have the same but the um the actual
sequence of updates or moves is somehow
constrained so the movement on the same
free energy surface is is somehow
constrainted to be different so I'd have
to know precisely what the algorithms
are um it probably is the case I'm just
guessing um that they probably don't
have quite the same um objective
function or or and Oran point of view
the free energy principle implicit
generative model um so the the chimeric
um um
self-organization is a reflection of the
fact that um um not everything is trying
to has the same gen model and there for
by definition will not have the same
free energy um functional so that that
does complicate the situation and makes
it more interesting in fact um you know
from the point of view of this this kind
of uh requisite variety um but now i'
forgotten the the your your actual
question um which I did have an answer
to what can you remind me what the sure
sure it's so so what these algorithms
have in common with some of the things
that you and and Chris fields have said
about particles and things and and other
people of part which is different from
what happens in biology right if if if
in biology I said look this cell is
exchanging information with that cell
and it's making decisions the next
question is excellent what's the
mechanism right like what like show me
show me the the the explicit uh set of
steps by which the cell does that but
but here we don't have that and and
presumably you know when we get down to
particles and things we don't have that
either so what's what what's the status
of these all these amazing things that
they're doing without a a a mechanism to
explicitly do it right um I'm going to
give you an answer which um um comes
from conversations with philosophers of
maths people like Maxell
ramstead that that question technically
would be answered um by um appeal to
what is a mechanics so a mechanics is um
for example the basy mechanics of the
free energy principle or lran or
classical mechanics and uh
um certain um Dynamics
um uh you
know non- dissipative or conservative so
or quantum mechanics um where um you
can't uh you you you you have to focus
exclusively on the on the dissipative uh
Dynamics so the
mechanics um is a description of the
realization of something um where the
thing usually conforms to a principle of
least action so this is where this is a
sort of deflationary answer to your
question that the mechanics in and of
itself is an emergent property of a
variational principle of leased action
that can be cast in gauge theoretic
terms or
in or in terms of things like maximum
entropy principles so there are
principles um that just describe the
shape the SpaceTime shape of our world
these um give rise to and usually you
know you can usually uh reduce all
physics principles to principles of
least action the the know the straight
line the path of least effort um um and
once you've written written down your
Principle as a principle um of least
action then the particular functional
form of the system to which that
principle applies then gives you a
mechanics and then that now um acquires
a teeology in conversation but only in
conversation you don't need the mechanic
the mechanics does not engineer anything
it is just an expression of the
principle of least action um so very
much in the spirit of basic mechanics I
was saying before the free energy
principle is just a description of
things that self-organize
you may or may not want to then go on
and say oh well this self-organization
could be described theologically as
self- evidencing or active inference or
decision making or basil cognition or
distributed intelligence you don't have
to do that but it sometimes it can be
very useful when talking to somebody
else about it to to to te logically
frame it like that and that I think is
your mission I I think that's what
you're bringing to the table in in the
widest sense you are saying that the
mechanics of biotic self
organization have a certain techology
which is almost isomorphic to the same
Tey of find in Psychiatry or
immunotherapy or climate change uh and
we just got to find the crosscutting
themes so the mechanics the
mechanisms um are really just
theological unpacking of of of the
mechanics so in this instance I gave you
an example before that simply um the
algorithm uh to implement the algorithm
which is probably a series of Boolean
operators would need certain inputs they
need arguments and they need certain
outputs those are the act the sensory
active States those those Define now the
Markoff blanket um that so you know
taking the input is basically whatever
my neighbor Neighbors value uh whatever
I can see and what I can see is my
neighbor's value and it has has to be a
neighbor I can't see you know the one
for you I can't see somebody a long way
away so that defines the input and the
output is my particular number that's
what I broadcast but I only broadcast it
in a Lo in in a local sense so when you
starting to express things in terms of a
um a teolog of
self-organization um of the kind that
people use in in you know in the free
energy principle I think you're then
you're quite licensed to say well this
is just a description for example of
electrochemical signaling you know
there's there's no no magic is this is
this is this is the mechanism it just
means that there has to be a local
signal that um reports or has some um um
morphism between my state and um um and
you know everything that is not me um
and we find multiple instances of this
in uh in in biology at different temper
and spatial scales and you know the more
you drill down the more you actually
specify what it is the more mechanistic
you it will become but you know at the
end of the day that's just the mechanics
you're talking about so if you know if
you wanted to describe self-organization
of massive bodies that had no
dissipative aspects to them you know the
motion of the planets for example if you
if you take yourself can pretend you're
Kepler um yeah what is the mechanics of
motion of the he Heavenly Bodies they
lran conservative mechanics that inherit
from the principle of least action that
um you know has a relatively simple form
before Einstein came along um in terms
of uh you know um um energy conservation
you know and uh all that is implicit in
a path of a path of least you know the
least action uh least action principle
so that would be his kind of mechanics
and you start to invent things like
gravity and mass and you know and talk
about the tileology of massive bodies
being attracted to each other uh and
that would be you know quite comfortably
received as a an intuitive mechanistic
explanation for the thing at hand which
in this instan is the motion of heavenly
bodies you I I don't see there's any
real problem from your point of view
you've already told story you've already
got the mechanics uh it's just you know
a question of um showing how Universal
this kind of mechanics is and uh and
Universal in in the special context of
local interactions um and all the uh all
the consequences of having a principle
uh or the principles that would apply to
self-organizing systems out of
equilibrium or non-equilibrium um uh
self-organization biotics self
organization what kind of mechanics must
be in play um and then you can give
particular Exemplar and talk about
gravity or ell intercellular signaling
or um you know and the locality of that
does that make sense yeah yeah yeah yeah
um and I guess um Adam did you want to
say anything before I because I've I've
got a little more um another okay so so
this is kind of the uh the the really
kind of far out thing in and feel free
to tell me that this is not a good
analogy and you know kind of too too too
far out but um I I was thinking I was
thinking about the analogy of us trying
to analyze these algorithms and what it
is that what are the causes of their
behavior as we observe them and trying
to uh analogize to uh in a in a um you
know biological or maybe in a
psychological psychiatric context where
you have what you think is the algorithm
and maybe that's what your subject
thinks is the cause of their actions and
maybe that's what you think is the cause
of their actions but it turns out that
there's this underlying Dynamic that is
it's it's an extra goal that you didn't
know because you couldn't you you didn't
see it in the uh in the steps of the of
the policies that they're supposedly
following and I wonder if this is a sort
of really basil kind of I don't know I
just just a really basil kind of
Behavioral analysis that might be
important for uh larger and more complex
systems in the sense of finding um
underlying
goals for for for complex behaviors that
are not to be found in the by
enumerating the mechanisms that you know
that are there which is you know like
basically basically looking at the
tendency to Cluster uh as a as a hidden
motivation for their behavior if I can
use this kind of like psychological term
what do you think about that is that is
that silly or or are there oh no no I I
think that's you exactly the application
of these principles and the attendant
mechanics you know in terms of say vote
in Dynamics um or geopolitical um um and
um or just a spread of information on
the internet you
know um I I think some really important
deep questions there and and um things
you know why is it that almost
inevitably whenever you look at some um
ideological political or theological
commitment everybody's 5050 you know
Trump versus Biden brexit versus stay
you know wherever you look U the only
evolutionary stable strategy on or fre
energy minimizing not an equilibrium
steady state is you know usually a 5050
but of course that can be subdivided
within what this this 50% there's
another 50% in a in a sort of self-
similar way all the way down so there
some must be something generically um
very important you diversal about that
and I would imagine that's you you will
see that kind of clustering it's
interesting I didn't realize I I I
didn't read it careful enough to realize
you had this sort of um that the actual
order wins out at the end of the day so
you get the increase and then the
decrease in clustering that that was
interesting it I would be if I was a
young man working for as you for you as
a PhD student I'd like to put a bit of
noise on the numbers and just see if you
can keep it alive and dynamic and see if
that clustering and that Chic um uh
Behavior look at its Dynamics and you
know
something in dynamical systems theory
called frustration that you get in these
um um in these chimeric um situations
when You' broken detail balance like
this which which may be a good metaphor
for the voting Dynamics for example uh
so I know I think it's a very sensible
idea I'm just reminded have you read
that paper by Connor
Hines um and if not I'll send it to you
so he's he's he he um he was making an
analogy between um gives energy and free
energy um in terms of
exchanging ideas um as a model of
um Collective behavior um and um it
maybe you'll find some interesting
ethological references or
references to
that yeah interesting that you know the
thing about the thing about them being
pulled apart at the end so so one way
one of the things that we we did was to
ask okay how how strong would this
tendency to Cluster be if you if you
didn't have this super overlying you
know basic physics of this world that
eventually is just going to yank you
apart and and one way to do that is to
allow repeat numbers so if I allow
repeat numbers then you can have a long
run of fives and the first half of them
could be one algot type the second half
could be the other and the actual
sorting algorithm would be perfectly
happy to keep them as is because the
fives are the you know so so we did that
and and when you do that you find out
that yeah if you let them do that it
actually goes higher the the the
tendency to Cluster is actually higher
that you know so there's this like
competing you know and and again looking
at it it almost it almost provides a
very minimal model of of the existential
uh sort of I don't know uh way of life
facing living systems right that that
the physics of the world are like trying
to grind you down but but in the
meantime you can do some interesting
things that are not not incompatible
with them there's no magic I mean it
does the algorithm there's no you know
there's no errors but but but yet not
quite what what the you know what what
the end goal is going to be according to
the actual physics of the system yeah